McClure mss. V, 1890-1929 LMC 1691
Lilly Library
McClure mss. V
1890-1929
Lilly Library
McClure, S. S. (Samuel Sidney), 1857-1949
LMC 1691
2 Boxes 2 standard
The McClure mss. V, 1890-1929, consists of the papers of editor S. S. (Samuel Sidney) McClure, 1857-1949.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 1976
Biographical Note
Samuel Sidney McClure was born on February 17, 1857 in County Antrim, Ireland, the son of Thomas and Elizabeth (Gaston) McClure. In 1864, his father died, so in 1866 his mother emigrated to the United States and settled in Porter County, Indiana. McClure attended Valparaiso high school from 1871 to 1874. He then enrolled in Knox College, graduating in 1882, and he would be elected a trustee of the College in 1894. He married Harriet Sophia Hurd, whom he had met at Knox College, on September 4, 1883, and they had five children: Eleanor, Elizabeth (Bess), Mary, Robert and their adopted son Enrico. From 1882 through the end of 1883, McClure edited the Wheelman, a bicycling magazine. The following spring he worked at the DeVinne printing house before moving on to work for The Century Company from April to October 1884. On November 16, 1884 McClure started McClure's Syndicate, the first newspaper syndicate in the United States. In 1893, McClure founded McClure's Magazine which was famous for its "muckraking" journalism and fiction pieces written by such respected writers as Jack London, Ida Tarbell, Upton Sinclair, Rudyard Kipling, Sir Arthur Conan Doyle, Robert Louis Stevenson, Willa Cather, and Lincoln Steffens. McClure would also use his magazine to promote the pedagogical theories of Maria Montessori after meeting her in 1910. After McClure's Magazine was met with a series of staff changes and financial difficulties, McClure turned to his own publishing pursuits. In 1914, he published My Autobiography, ghostwritten by Willa Cather who had worked as a managing editor at McClure's Magazine. During World War I he was concerned with matters of peace, joining Henry Ford aboard his "Peace Ship" in 1915 and publishing a book entitled Obstacles to Peace in 1917. From 1915 to 1917, McClure also became co-owner with Edward A. Rumely of The Evening Mail. McClure traveled frequently throughout his life, crossing the Atlantic 149 times and making trips to Europe, Palestine, Egypt, and China. McClure's Magazine and McClure's syndicate were both eventually sold, and McClure himself died on March 21, 1949. He is buried in Galesburg, Illinois.
Scope and Content Note
The correspondence in the collection is concerned chiefly with McClure's financial affairs and the sale of The McClure Press in February 1925. Included are letters exchanged with Edward Aloysius Rumely, June 8, 1911 to February 10, 1914 (11 letters); McClure's naturalization certificate, July 10, 1916; a letter from Mother Rhoda Alice, Jewish Christian mystic, with brochures and pictures, Nov. 16, 1917; and an undated letter from John Sanburn Phillips. As a result of McClure's tour as a roving correspondent in China in 1917, he received a letter from William Stuart Howe, dated August 22, 1917, concerning the relationship of China and Japan and the "diffusion of the Anglo-Saxon spirit."
A group of typed and printed materials originally from the files of Benjamin W. Huebsch of Viking Press contains items about Henry Ford's Peace Expedition on the Oscar II.
A large number of photographs includes those taken on the Chinese tour, 1917, Egyptian tour, 1901-1902, French tour, 1899-1901, those of Samuel Sidney McClure, his associates among whom was John Sanburn Phillips, and the McClure and Hurd families. Some of these are in a folio including those used to illustrate Success Story by Peter Lyon.
Completing the collection are a biographical folder of printed pieces filed with the correspondence, and a folio containing a typed copy of The High Cost of Impatience by Curtis P. Brady.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged following original order.
Related Material
See McClure mss., McClure mss. II, McClure mss. III, McClure mss. IV, and McClure mss. VI, also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Journalism; China--Description and travel; McClure, S. S. (Samuel Sidney), 1857-1949; Henry Ford Peace Expedition (Date of meeting or treaty signing: (1915-1916).); Oscar II (Ship)
- Correspondence., 1890-1916 (Box 1)
- Correspondence., 1917-1929 (Box 1)
- Benjamin W. Huebsch Papers about the Ford Peace Ship (Box 1)
- Biographical Materials. Printed (Box 1)
- Photographs. McClure, Samuel Sidney (Box 2)
- Photographs. McClure, Samuel Sidney by Arnold Genthe (Box 2)
- Photographs. McClure and/or his associates (Box 2)
- Photographs. McClure and Hurd Families (Box 2)
- Photographs. French tour, 1899-1901 (Box 2)
- Photographs. Egyptian tour, 1901-1902 (Box 2)
- Photographs. Chinese tour, 1917 (Box 2)
- Photographs. McClure, Cather, Tarbell, Irwin, in a park, 1924 (Box 2)
- Photographs (Folio [1])
- Brady, Curtis P.The High Cost of Impatience. (Folio [2])